So "Oh boy I sure do love being perceived
as a gifted child, I hope I don't end up
as being a perfectionist... perfectionist
burnout with...
burnt out I suppose, with depression,
anxiety, unfulfilled expectations
and no real interests or goals".
So this is something that someone
cross-posted to our subreddit, you know
it's a meme. We've had a couple of
streams about burnout and gifted kids,
so today what I'd like to talk to you
all a little bit about is
the pathway from gifted child to burnt
out perfectionist
as well as sort of the way that society
actually sets gifted children up
to kind of fail
So I know it's kind of interesting, but
when we think about a gifted child
we think about we perceive
gifted as an advantage
but in my experience working with a lot
of gifted children, it's not always an
advantage and in fact often times
it can be a burden,
and so I've seen this a lot in our
community I've worked with a lot of
people who kind of fall into that this category,
I suppose I sort of fall
into it as well.
Where I grew up kind of... I'm gifted, right?
So like school was easy for me, I
was told from a very young age
that I was smart,
I was also kind of held accountable for
like... not studying, right? There like I'd
kind of like not study very much and
maybe get a B+ or an A-.
And my teachers would tell my parents
the same thing every single
parent-teacher conference, they'd always
say "well, if Alok look just applied
himself he would be the best
student in the class",
"If he only just like studied more
he'd be the best student in
the class", right, they were like "He's
super smart, he has a lot of potential",
right, so they use these words like...
they talk about how smart I am, they talk
about all the potential I have, and if I
just applied myself I'd be you know...
I'd be such a...
I'd be the best student.
So it's kind of interesting because we
perceive giftedness as an advantage,
but as one of my teachers once told me
we'll kind of get to
this towards the end,
they once explained to me that um... this
is in... in... not in medical school, but when
I was training to become a psychiatrist,
I had a supervisor who once told me that
gifted... gifted children are special needs
children and what that literally means
is that like the needs of a child who's
gifted are actually different from the
average child, and the parents who
recognize that and recognize that this
child is going to need like a slightly
different structure, a different
curriculum or a different way of being
raised, are the ones that end up sort of
doing a really good job, and oddly enough
in her clinical experience she found
that much like any other
special needs children um...
you know, kids that were not
treated... appropriately, despite their
gifts, were the ones that kind of
struggled. So this statement, when I first
heard it, I thought was like absolutely
ridiculous, kind of  blew my mind a little
bit, but I respected the supervisor a lot
and I started thinking about it.
So what I'd like to share with you all
today is sort of the pathway
that a gifted child takes,
how a society treats them, how parents
treat them, the kind of struggles they
face, or the influences that they have,
let's not even call it a struggle
because it may not be a struggle and
then sort of how they end up. So I'd like
to kind of share with... that with
you all today, okay?
So the first thing that tends to happen
is when a child is gifted they te...
school tends to be easy, right?
So if you kind of think
about it developmentally,
there are a lot of different things that
happen in school, so let's talk about
school. So school is a place where you
get... you socialize, right? So you get
socialization skills, it's a place that
you learn and people think that school
is primarily about learning, and it is
primarily about learning,
but it's just not about
learning that the subject material,
so sure we learn like arithmetic and
mathematics and all that kind of stuff,
we learn history and science
and all that good stuff,
but really school if you kind of
look at it developmentally, is a wonderful
opportunity to learn certain key things,
socialization is a really important piece,
the other thing is like habits and
how to study, and this is the first sort
of disadvantage that I think
gifted children sort of face,
is that you know if you're young and
you're gifted, school is so easy that you
sort of get by without the luxury of
studying and so we kind of perceive this
as an advantage, right, like if you have
to if you go through school and you
don't study like that's easy like
it's easy easy clap, right?
And so it is and that
sort of makes sense,
but the... the interesting thing that I
found is that oftentimes being
intelligent, especially when you're super
young as a kid, actually sets you up for
failure down the road, because
you never need to learn
the habituated study like technique,
that you kind of need to that...
that you need to succeed later on.
So for a normal kid what tends to happen is
like they don't have to study like in
first grade, but maybe like second grade
third grade, they have to learn how to
study like once a week, maybe they like
learn how to study the night before the
test because it doesn't
come easily to them
and then fourth grade fifth grade, now
you're... you're doing homework a couple
days a week, you know, you're studying two
or three days before the test, then you
kind of hit middle school, where maybe
you're studying like four days before
the test, and so there's this very
graduated sense of increasing
responsibility as you go further
and further in school
and it's sort of designed that way, right?
We're not... like no teacher has a six... six year
old that they're like... giving
fourteen hours of homework a week to, it's just
absurd, and then at the top end of the
spectrum in terms of study habits and
what we demand of students, you have
something like let's say law school or
medical school or things like that, where
people are regularly studying like sixty
hours a week, eighty hours a week in medical
school because you know people have... have
grown up and have built enough of a
study habit where they can actually
handle that pace of study.
So what happens with the gifted kid, so
the gifted kid you know, when you sort of
level up your skill to level one like in
the first grade and then you level up
your studying skill to level two in the
second grade and level three in the
third grade. So the gifted kid never
actually has to like grind that xp for
levels like one through five
of studying habits
and so they sort of managed to get Bs
or As without really minimal with
minimal studying or no studying at all,
and then seventh grade rolls around
eighth grade rolls around, they start to
struggle a little bit maybe they get Bs,
they're still not learning how to study
because they sort of skipped that part of ...
of the you know... the skill building
and we'll kind of get to that later,
and then what tends to happen with gifted
kids is that they don't need to study,
don't need to study, don't need to study.
And then they hit a wall,
they finally get into some kind of
situation where their
raw intellect cannot...
is no longer sufficient to handle the
schoolwork that they're
supposed to handle,
but they've trained themselves at that
point, they've customized themselves at
that point to managing
school with raw intellect,
and so when that kind of falls short
they like they really kind of really hit
a wall, it's a very very
hard cliff to to overcome,
and so this is kind of the first thing
that that sort of shoots gifted kids in
the foot and this also leads to kind of
this idea of perfectionism and burnout,
because then they like you know then
they... they struggle a lot, they don't
understand why they can't do it, they...
they try, they know they're smart,
everyone's talking to them about
potential, they start to feel really bad
about themselves. So the first kind of
interesting thing that gifted kids run
into is the fact that they sort of don't
develop the proper study habits, because
you know as a six-year-old it's kind of
not your fault, because like you're not
mature enough as a six-year-old to
realize, like "Oh I need you know to have
good study habits. So even though the
teacher said this last tuesday and I
understand that I don't need to study,
I'm going to sit down and like practice
my study habits". It doesn't make any
sense, it's like completely artificial,
so that's the first thing that happens,
is that they kind of hit this wall of... of
you know not being able to study.
The second thing to consider is the
expectation, so another thing that really
leads gifted kids kind of
down the wrong path, is the burden
of expectation that's placed
upon them, so from a very young age
they're told "Oh you're gifted", "You're
smart", "You're special", "You have so much
potential", and so what that starts to do,
is it constructs like a very very lofty
goal in their minds, right. So I'm going
to use kind of an analogy which is kind
of like... you know if I think about an
amazing home, like I think about a
mansion, it can have a beautiful
blueprint and I can buy a gigantic piece
of land, and I can look at that and I can
say like "Oh... like this... this home or this...
this blueprint has so much potential".
And sometimes we kind
of forget that like, you can
have like... you can have a
blueprint for a mansion, but that's gonna
actually take way more work to achieve
than like building a shack. So the other
really interesting thing that... that we
sort of kind of get wrong societally, is
that we assume that
when someone is gifted,
things are actually going to be easier
for them, that they need to work less to
accomplish the same amount,
but in my experience living up to a
gifted child's potential involves more
work, it's sort of like you know it's
just like building a shack versus
building a mansion, like sure the mansion
is capable of so much more than the shack
is capable of, but let's not forget for a
moment, that the amount of effort that it
goes into building a mansion is actually
way more than what's required to build a
shack. This is the second place that
gifted kids kind of get tripped up,
because everyone around
is looking at them and
they're sort of saying
"Oh like this is an amazing mansion", like
"You could build such an amazing mansion".
And we all kind of forget for a moment
that like... actually living up to that
potential is very very difficult and
requires a lot more of an investment,
than building a shack.
And so this gap between what people
expect of you and also the idea that
things should be easier for you,
kind of compound on themselves and sort
of end up with gifted kids kind of
feeling like they're... they're failing at
everything, right? Because
they have all this potential
and they're not they're
just not living up to it.
So the other thing that we'll see in
gifted kids is that, what... what tends to
happen is that they will put
in some amount of work,
but they're expecting a mansion, when
all they've really put in is
as much as building a shack.
I may have lost you a little bit there,
but let me just explain,
so you know what a
gifted kid will do is
they'll like look at their peers, right,
and they'll say like "Oh like this person
did this and they're able to accomplish
this, so like I should be able to do that too"
and so if you look at your neighbors
who are building a shack and they're
like whoa they went to *Leroy Merlin* and
they got like a hundred pounds of wood, and
they built their shack over a weekend,
and then like you go and get your a hundred
pounds of wood from *Leroy Merlin* and you
start like... brought to you by *Leroy Merlin*,
I suppose, um... and you start building your
mansion like... I know it sounds kind of
weird, but you know a hundred pounds of wood
may be enough to build a shack, but it's
nowhere near enough to build a mansion.
And then what gifted kids will do is
they'll look at like the foundation that
they've laid with a hundred pounds of
wood, and they'll be like "Where's the..."
"I don't even have a shack" like you know
it's... it's like they look at what they've
accomplished, when they put in the same
amount of energy as someone else, and
they get really confused because this
person has a complete shack over here
and like I have like barely the
beginnings of a mansion. And so then that
sort of negatively impacts them, they
start to like feel like they're actually
inferior to these other people, because
they've been told "Oh you're smarter than
the kid next door", like "Why the hell is
the kid next door getting into college
and like you're not even getting into
college" and so it all sort of... sort of...
sort of compounds, right, because even for
the gifted kid, they're not trying to
build a shack, because they've been told...
they've been... they're gifted their entire
life. So it's not enough to be average if
you're gifted, so what you have to do is
you try to, you know, build a mansion,
because that's what you've been
told... that you're capable of, that's the
expectation you set for yourself. And
then you're... you're left kind of
scratching your head and wondering like
why you don't even have a shack yet, even
though you studied for a month and they
studied for a month, you're not getting
as much as that they're getting,
and it's kind of super bizarre, right?
Because we don't we just don't think
about it that way, we think that if
you're gifted that means that everything
should be easier for you, that it not
only they may need a hundred pounds of
wood to build a shack, but you should be
able to build a shack with 50 pounds of
wood, it should be easier for you, but it
turns out paradoxically being harder.
And then we sort of end up with kind of
the final state of a gifted kid, which if
we kind of think about it internally, is
a state of like really shame and low
self-esteem. So all this stuff kind of
compounds, right? Like you're told you're
smart, so you set this expectation of
what you're capable of, like way up here,
and then like you know first grade goes
by and you're up here, second grade goes
by and you're up here, third grade goes
by and you're up here, boom, boom, boom,
fourth grade, fifth grade, sixth grade,
tenth grade eleventh grade and then you kind
of tank, right, and as you go to college
suddenly like you don't have the study
skills involved, and now in the gap
between what you're capable of and what
you actually accomplish, this gap is
where shame comes from this, is the shame
gap that gifted kids
inevitably fall into,
which is when they fall short of what
their expectations are, and
this could be once again
due to the fact that you're... you know
you're setting out to build a mansion
and you ended up not even building a
shack, right? So all of these
discrepancies between your expectations
and your accomplishments
in that gap, and the bigger the gap is,
the more it's filled with shame,
so then what happens is kids are ashamed,
right? Because they should be doing more,
they should be doing better
and then like the shame then further
compounds and makes it hard to find
motivation and this is where you kind of
get burnout. So then like you have these
gifted kids and you're like "Hey man just
like go to a community college, you don't
have to go to an ivy league school...
school, you don't have to go to like
Harvard or Stanford or MIT. Just like go
to your local community college" and in
that comes a bunch of shame, because
you've been told your entire life that
you're better than that, right?
And so you start to develop this ego
of being a super smart kid, and then this
leads to avoidance of things, because all
you're left with is the identity of a
smart kid, so you can never even bring
yourself to go to community college,
because smart kids don't go to community
college. In your mind that's where the
stupid kids go and if you go to
community college then suddenly, you've
lived your entire life for 20 years
being told you're a smart kid, it's the
only... that's your biggest strength, it's
the one that everyone keeps talking
about, and now like suddenly you have to
relegate yourself to being a stupid kid
and in that gap is where the shame lives,
in that gap is where the ego lives, okay?
So it's really really hard, right? Because
you're set up with these expectations,
people don't really acknowledge that...
because you're capable of a lot, it's
actually going to take like a lot of
work to take that potential
and bring it to fruition,
right? And that's like... that's the biggest
thing is, people just lose sight of the
fact that building a mansion actually
takes more work than building a shack,
and your entire life people have told
you like you should build this mansion
because that's what you're capable of.
And so then we kind of get to "All right,
so like what do we do about it?", right, so
if you're a gifted kid who's kind of
perfectionistic and burnt out, and like
society has sort of set you up this way.
I'm not saying that you're not
individually responsible as well, but I
do think that there's a whole reason so
when we have like a generation of burnt
out gifted kids, I think we have to be
fair and be a little bit scientific and
kind of acknowledge that this may not be
like an individual problem, right? We've
got a generation of kids like this, like
maybe there's something societal going
on and I think paradoxically we sort of
set these kids up to
struggle, and so then the question
becomes "Okay, like what do we do about it?"
So the first thing you should do if
you're a gifted kid is to stop
comparison, right? Like comparison is... is
the foundation of getting
out of this problem,
because as long as you are comparing
yourself and this is part of the issue
is that if you think
about the word gifted,
what does the word gifted imply, it is a
word that has no meaning
outside of a comparative framework, you
guys get that? The only way you can be
gifted is if there are other
people who are not gifted,
and so essentially what happens is like
the whole idea of a gifted kid only
exists in relationship to another kid,
and so what we find in the minds of
gifted kids is that they're comparing
themselves all the time "Oh I don't want
to go to community college that's where
the stupid people go", "Oh I don't know
like why I can't do what my friend is
capable of like, he's able to do so much
why am I not able to do so much?" "I have
an older sibling who did fantastic
and now I have big shoes to fill", right?
There's so much comparison, all of the
expectations that gifted kids have don't
come from themselves, right?
Because if you actually based your
expectations on what you're capable of,
you'd be capable of A, B, C, D, or an F,
that's what that would be a realistic
expectation, but instead you create these
artificial expectations that are based
on comparison and why do gifted kids do
that? Because it starts with their
parents, it starts with their teachers.
We're all told that we're gifted, which
is by definition a comparison
to all of the other kids,
and so then what happens is you're
looking over at the shack, and you've got
this blueprint for a mansion and they
give you some wood and then you try to
build the mansion and like you don't
even have a roof, when this person has a
completely built shack, and then you kind
of look at yourself well like "Man I must
be like a super idiot", right like and
it's just it's so bizarre that when we
set up this kind of... when we start with
this framework of a comparison,
we sort of doom ourselves to failure,
because there's like... we're just...
it's just it's never going to work,
because you can't ever
base the expectations of your life and
what you're capable of based on what
someone else is doing, right?
If someone else is happy studying
chemical engineering it doesn't mean
that you're going to be happy studying
chemical engineering. If somebody else is
happy dating someone of the opposite sex
it doesn't mean that you're going to be
happy dating someone of the opposite sex.
The whole point is as individuals, as
humans we're individuals and if you're a
gifted kid the first thing you've got to
do is let go of all comparison.
So next thing is to
recognize that your road is going to be
a rough one, right? So like when someone
sets out to build a mansion, they know in
their mind that like: "This is
gonna take a while", right?
You can't expect to build a mansion in
the same amount of time it would take
someone to build a shack,
and so if you're a gifted kid and you
expect a lot
from yourself, okay?
Recognize that this is going to be a
long road and the greater your potential
is the longer it's going to take for you
to get there, and this is something that
I can understand in hindsight, like so I
grew up as a gifted kid and was like in
you know the special classes or whatever,
I actually still remember when I was in
eighth grade my grades started to dip
and when i went to high school
um... I didn't qualify for... based on my
grades like my high school was like "Yeah
he needs to be in like regular english,
he can't be in like advanced english" or
"He doesn't meet the criteria for
advanced english and so my parents were
really really not happy with that,
because they have... they have such a smart
boy you know "He's so smart, he just needs
to apply himself", so they went to the
school and I remember having a meeting
with the... the... honors english teacher or
whatever and then he's like "Do you want
to be in this class and I was like "Yeah,
I want to be in the class" and my parents
were like "Yeah he should be..." "He belongs,
he belongs in the class",
right? And so the teacher was like "Okay,
fine", because you know...
I mean you're not gonna... you know there
are some parents that could potentially
be annoying, so you're like whatever
and so I ended up being in the class
that I really didn't belong to
and I really didn't do very well,
right? because I didn't have the work
ethic, but it propagates sort of this
idea of like you can handle it,
so like I started off you know going on
the wrong track kind of like in... in high
school it took me...
I... took me five years to graduate
from college right with a 2.5 gpa,
took me another three or four years to
even get into medical school,
and so like my road has been long
and like that's just sometimes what it
takes if you're a gifted kid, right?
You take the scenic route in life, so
oftentimes people would
ask me you know like
about stuff, when I remember
when I was going to.. when
I started medical school and I saw
friends of mine right who were... who I was
in high school with, they're already
fully trained doctors and you know
flying around, and all that good stuff,
and I'm just like starting medical
school, and I was like "Yeah I took the
scenic route in life". And so recognize
that if you're a gifted kid, like it's a
long road, like you're not going to do
things faster, you're not
going to build a mansion
as fast as someone else is going to
build a shack. The other thing to
recognize about it being a long road if
you're a gifted kid, is don't expect to
see the form of your
mansion for a long time,
when other people have built their
shacks you will still just have the
foundation of the mansion, it's not going
to have a roof for a long time, it's not
going to have windows for a long time. So
this is the other problem
that gifted kids run into,
is as they put in an equal amount of
effort compared to their colleagues, they
actually see less return on their
investment, and that in turn shatters
their motivation and what
makes them want to give up,
right? Because "I'm putting in all this
effort, I'm still not seeing anything yet",
so it's a long road. Be patient with
yourself and try your best not to
compare to other people.
The last thing to kind of consider is
that... is the shame, so gifted kids
oftentimes struggle a lot with
self-esteem and shame, and that once
again is because their expectations are
up here and their
performance is down here, right?
And so in that gap is where
your shame is going to live
and so as long as there is a gap in what
you expect from yourself,
with what you accomplish,
you will have shame, and the solution to
that oddly enough is one
of two ways, right?
One is you can actually
live up to the expectations that you
have, right, so you can actually shoot up
here and land up here, so you can go to
an ivy league school or whatever, right?
You can go, you can start...
you can do a tech startup
or whatever, like... you can like
do everything that everyone has always
known you're capable of doing, so you can
actually hit all of those metrics, that's
one option, then the shame will go away
or what you can do
is let go of your expectations
and bring yourself down here, because the
shame exists in the gap so even if you
accept yourself as being like sort of a
failure, oddly enough the shame will go
away and as you accept yourself as you
are, which is not wasted potential, but
like in the present, like you are
everything that you're capable of.
Everything that you've ever been capable
of is exactly what you've achieved and
once you sort of take that attitude,
bring your expectations down to here you,
will be amazed at like what happens to
your motivation and what
you are truly capable of,
but you can't achieve it as long as
there is that shame gap, right? Like in
terms of performance. So questions.
anyway so let me just kind of summarize,
so I think that like
you know we see this a lot
where a lot of people are gifted
and we think of that as an advantage, but
like I was saying
earlier I think that...
you know sometimes being gifted comes
with its own set of needs
and by properly addressing those needs
we can avoid some of these things, like
gifted kids you know feeling
ashamed of themselves, gifted kids
you know not like comparing themselves
to like all the other normal kids and
and finding themselves lacking,
um... and also that we have to kind of
acknowledge that our school system is
sort of set up in a particular way, that
oftentimes causes gifted kids to stumble
and through understanding like how a
gifted kid, you know a child who is
gifted, becomes an adult who's
perfectionistic and burnt out.
We have to understand that whole life
cycle in order to sort of start taking steps
to change it. Um... okay "So I'm sure you've been
asked this question before and have answered before,
so feel free to tell me where I can
finally answer this question. How are you
able to get accepted to harvard medical
school, let alone medical school alone
with such a low gpa when that is such a
critical deciding factor?
How did i stand out?" So that's a great
question, so the short answer is so I... I
did some amount of graduate education, so
I did a master's degree to boost my gpa.
The second thing that I did, I didn't go
to harvard for medical school I went to
Tufts for medical school and then I did
my psychiatry training at Harvard, at
Mass General Mclean Hospital.
And so the short answer of like how I
wound up there is
like one step at a time,
so you have to do you know in each of
those things involved like a reality check or some degree of
humility in terms of like thinking, like
"I actually don't belong at harvard" like
"I'm never going to wind up there", I had
to accept that, right? Let alone
get into medical school,
and the more that I accepted like... I...
I did a lot of things, that were you know,
humbling to say the least, I wouldn't
quite say undignified, but I had to
really let go of a lot of ego and like
take one step at a time. It also took
perseverance, I mean I applied to one hundred
twenty medical schools before I got into a
single one and that was the
break that I needed, and then
like understanding, having all
that failure behind me, I really
worked hard in medical school
and really tried to excel,
and then I actually did an away rotation,
for those of you don't know what that is
or for those of you do know what that is,
so I basically did an audition rotation
at Harvard, which is like super
competitive, you show up there with a
bunch of other people who want to go
there and it's basically like a test,
it's like a month-long test of what
you're capable of, and I did really well,
so thankfully I had set up you know a
lot of good stuff over
the last eight years
in terms of being myself and like owning
the person that I was, and not being
ashamed of the fact that I failed,
and you know recognizing that most of
the students most of the other students
who were auditioning... um...
were four years younger than I was,
that I was actually older
than some of the residents there,
despite the fact that like they were
evaluating me, right? So like there's
someone two years younger
who's like giving me a grade,
so navigating all that stuff was
difficult, but I did a good job at it and
stayed focused and that's how I wound up
at harvard. So I trained there for four years and that's where
I'm faculty now... right? but it's all about like letting go of the ego.
Um... "How do you lower expectations?", uh... you
lower expectations by accepting what you're capable of,
like actually. And so expectation and... and
acceptance are at opposite
ends of the spectrum,
okay? So
practicing acceptance
is how you
lower expectations, so let me
give you guys an example, so
the theme today is Jnana Yoga,
right? So like let me think about a Jnana
Yoga exercise to let go of expectations.
Um... let me just think about this for a second...
so here's a good example of a Jana Yoga
exercise, actually I don't know
if this is a good example,
this is one of the ones that I feel less
confident this is maybe a
bad example of a Jnana  Yoga
exercise, so for the next
month or two months when you go to a restaurant,
and someone asks you what you want to...
want... what you want to order just tell
the waiter to surprise you,
just tell them "Surprise me",
and then pay attention
to your enjoyment or lack
of enjoyment of the food,
right? So when we go to restaurants,
we have expectations and
if we think about the least...
the worst experience that you can have
at a restaurant is not
actually to have bad food,
it's to expect really good food and get
bad food, that's actually worse than
getting bad food. If you know a
restaurant is crap and you go there, and
you order something, the food that you
get is crap like what were you expecting,
it's totally fine actually, right? We do
that every day, like if you go to a fast
food like McDonald's or Taco Bell or
whatever, like you're not expecting you
know like a gourmet meal, you're just
expecting some like
mediocre, arguably incredibly tasty,
depending on whether you're getting a
mexican pizza or not,
which you can't
get anymore because
they're out of sad,
But... so like a lot of...
if you guys want to
really understand, so this is the way
that Jnana Yoga works, if you really want to
understand expectation and acceptance,
you have to put yourself in situations
that are like free from expectation,
and you can't put yourself in a
situation, because the expectation
doesn't come from the situation, right?
It's even... that's... even what
I said was kind of wrong,
you have to practice messing
with your expectations, so go to
restaurant just say "Surprise me"
or you can ask if they don't know like
if they're taking it back, you can say
"What's good here?" "Okay I'll take that",
right, if you've got dietary restrictions,
tell them about the dietary restrictions,
and just like... and then you're like "But
what if I don't like the food that I get?",
well yeah, I mean that's the point, right?
So like just eat what
you get and see what happens,
and they're like "But I don't like it" and
it's like yes, so like pay attention to
that, and be like how hard is it for you
to order food that you're not gonna like
or you order without expectations, what's
it like to go to a restaurant and accept
that you're going to just get some
random pile of food, that could be
amazing and could be
something that you really dislike,
that's how you gain acceptance, that's
how you let go of expectations, by
literally going to a restaurant and like
actively letting them go
that is the Jnana Yoga,
and then you may discover all kinds of
cool things, right? You may even discover
for example that if you go to the
restaurant and you expect
crap, if you're like "This is going to be
an absolute train wreck, I'm gonna have
to go home and like have a bowl of
cereal after the meal",
it'll be really interesting
how much you enjoy your meal, it'll be
really interesting because in that
moment what you're doing is
letting go of the expectation, right?
And then like suddenly even if you
get crap it's not a big deal and if you
get something delicious it's like such a
huge win, and that's what it means to let
go of expectation, the more you let go of
expectation, the more you start to enjoy
life and the better life gets,
it's kind of bizarre So literally.
if you guys wanted Jnana
Yoga practice to let go of expectations
and earn acceptance, and you can't just
do this once right, so you can't like
wuss out of it, you have
to do it for a month,
presuming you're going to go out to eat
you know and you can afford that and all
that good stuff,
otherwise like make it
three months, like
you know do it for a while like commit
yourself "This is my life now",
gg get wrecked noobs. So... try it you
guys want to learn Jnana Yoga try it.
Okay, someone else is asking "How should a
parent teacher or manager support the
special needs of gifted people if what's
happening now is bad?" That's a great
question so I'll give you an example,
so sometimes I get parents that come
into my office, they have a kid who's addicted
to video games "Why is a kid
addicted to video games?", really simple
because video games match the pace of
the child, right? That's why... that's why
gifted kids in a nutshell, the reason
that gifted kids get addicted to video
games is one very very very simple
reason, can all be reduced to this,
games match the pace of
the child and school doesn't.
So you've got a kid, goes to school, gets
a worksheet, does the worksheet, I still
remember I... I had this experience. I
skipped the first grade
so this is what happened,
I went to a school
where you know I'd do a worksheet and
then like they'd give me another one, and
so in in my first day of first grade I
moved schools, I... I gave them... you know... I
got a worksheet, I did the worksheet, I
gave it back to them and I said "Can I
have the next one?" and she's like "What do
you mean the next one?" "It's like the next
one, like whatever's next like, I'm done
with this, we've got class for another forty-five
minutes, I'm done with this, can I have
the next one?" she's like "There is no next
one", I'm like "What?"
and it didn't take long, where like you
know she gave me the... then she evaluated
me and I got moved up a grade,
but the same problem there
and then eventually like what heck is
like school moves at the pace of like
the slowest person, now here's the really
addictive thing about a video game now,
imagine you're just bored at school,
because it's moving at a snail's pace,
right? Because there's like other
six-year-olds and like you're a
six-year-old too and maybe you're a
little smarter than the other
six-year-olds. Now enter a video game
what happens when you
don't beat level one?
You replay level one, and what happens
when you beat level one? You go straight
to level two and if you beat level two
you go straight to level three, you beat
level three you go
straight to level four.
So games perfectly match
the challenge that a human
being is capable of, right?
If you get stuck on a boss
in Dark Souls, like
you don't get to move past the boss,
because your parents make a phone call
to FromSoftware and they're like "Hey my
son is really good at video games, can
you please advance him past this boss
and stick him to the next boss?" it's like
you can't do that in Dark Souls, like
Dark Souls doesn't
care at all, right?
So like... kids get addicted to video games
because they perfectly match what you're
capable of, which is exactly what kids
like, there's this whole thing called
"intent to mastery", we teach all this
stuff to parents and things like that.
So what do you do if you've got a kid
who's gifted? You challenge them and you
don't rely on school to do it for you,
so when parents come to me and they're like
"I have a kid who's addicted to video
games, he's 16, he thinks school is...", I ask
him "Okay what do you think about school?"
like "School is boring!", then what I
do is... I... you know I make a
couple of phone calls and I'm like we're
gonna like you... so we were... I was back
when I was in Boston, a lot of cool
startups in Boston, so what I'll do is
we'll make some phone calls, we'll stick
them in an internship somewhere, like
we'll take some college-level internship,
it's some kind of startup, so like we'll
look around at like incubators from like
M.I.T or whatever, like Harvard, will be
like "Hey like there's a kid, do you guys
have any internship opportunities
available?"" and we'll stick him there and
he'll like be... he'll work there for the
summer and it like turns the kid right
around no more video games, because he's
actually like learning so I stuck one
kid in this startup, that was...
that there's an app, you take a picture
of a mole on your body and it tells you
the percentage chance
that the mole is cancerous,
right? So we stick the kid there,
we're like "Go help them!"
and then like sometimes the kid is like
"What am I supposed to do?", like
"You start by getting them coffee
and then maybe you'll learn something"
and then it's... it's actually fantastic,
like they do... they do really well you
challenge them, right? And because the
cool thing is that a lot of the startup
folks they sort of recognize, because
some of them are like misfits too. So
they're like "Okay there's like a kid
here, like let's put them to work" because
they recognize that "Okay you're sixteen, so
you know how to like manage SQL data...
databases?" and the kid is like "No"
they're like
"Google it and learn
and then you're going to
manage our SQL database next week"
and the kid is like "What?" and like "Yeah!"
and then suddenly the kid is like goes,
home he's not playing video games, he's
like reading about
SQL databases or whatever,
right? Just... just stick them... stick them
into it and challenge them
so as a parent you know or a teacher,
like I'd say like ask them so here's the
biggest mistake that parents and
teachers make with
gifted children, is that you
when... when a gifted child fails what we
tend to do is slow down, instead what you
need to do is speed up, it's absolutely
terrifying so if a gifted child is
failing what they need more than
anything else is a bigger challenge, not
like an easier environment, now you have
to make sure for a couple of other
things, like you need to make sure
there's not ADHD going, on depression
going on, learning disabilities or other
things like that going on, but in the
absence of all of those things challenge
them more not less,
ask them to do more, give them, put them
in positions of
leadership, right?
And just push them
because like it's so fulfilling when
when you're a take a kid in that
situation and you're like
"You're gonna need to do this thing" and
they're like "I can't do that thing" and
you're like "Okay, so then fail,
but try if you fail like no big deal, but
I'm not gonna... I'm not gonna expect less
of you", I know it's kind of paradoxical
because we just talked about
letting go of expectation,
but it's not really expectations, it's
really having faith in them it's a
subtle difference, but be like "I have
faith in you I think you can handle it
so like give it your best shot",
that's what you do you challenge them,
respect them, ins... instead
of expect things from them.